A Guide to the Papers of Chalmers Laughlin Gemmill 1914-(1960-1975)-1997
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
- Series IV: Research Interests
  - Dunglison
    - Dunglison Bibliography
      - Manuscript
        - Dunglison Bibliography draft (partial)-Lectures and Reviews n.d. (Box-folder 06:18)
        - Dunglison Bibliography draft (partial)-Reviews of "the Practice of Medicine" n.d. (Box-folder 06:19)
        - Dunglison Bibliography draft (partial)-General Therapeutics and Reviews n.d. (Box-folder 06:20)
        - Dunglison Bibliography draft (partial)-A New Dictionary of Medical Science n.d. (Box-folder 06:21)
        - Dunglison Bibliography draft (partial)-Medical Lexicon and Reviews n.d. (Box-folder 06:22)
        - Dunglison Bibliography draft (partial)-American Medical Library n.d. (Box-folder 06:23)
        - Dunglison Bibliography draft (partial)-Moxa n.d. (Box-folder 06:24)
        - Dunglison Bibliography draft (partial) n.d. (Box-folder 06:25)
        - Dunglison Bibliography draft (partial)-Introduction n.d. (Box-folder 06:26)
        - Dunglison Bibliography draft (partial)-Commentaries on Diseases of the Stomach and Bowels of Children n.d. (Box-folder 06:27)
        - Dunglison Bibliography draft (partial)-Introduction to the Study of Grecian and Roman Geography n.d. (Box-folder 06:28)
        - Dunglison Bibliography draft (partial)-Introduction and book locations n.d. (Box-folder 06:29)
        - Dunglison Bibliography-Outline n.d. (Box-folder 06:30)
        - Dunglison Bibliography draft (partial)-Table of Contents and Preface n.d. (Box-folder 06:31)
        - "A Bibliography of Robley Dunglison, MD", draft, marked up n.d. (Box-folder 06:32)
        - "A Bibliography of Robley Dunglison, MD", original n.d. (Box-folder 06:33)
    - Dunglison and Beaumont
      - Letters
        - Letter from Frances R Houston (University of Pennsylvania Medical Alumni Society) to C.L. Gemmill, with partial draft of Dunglison and Beaumont 1968 January 2 (Box-folder 06:34)
        - Correspondence between C.L. Gemmill and Lloyd G. Stevenson, re: Beaumont and Dunglison 1968 December 19-20 (Box-folder 06:35)
        - Letter from Estelle Brodman (Librarian, Washington University, St. Louis) to C.L. Gemmill, re: Beaumont 1969 April 4 (Box-folder 06:36)
      - Manuscript
        - Beaumont and Dunglison draft n.d. (Box-folder 06:37)
        - "Beaumont and Dunglison" marked up copy n.d. (Box-folder 06:38)
    - Dictionary
      - Letters
        - Letters from Arthur F. Stocker to C.L. Gemmill, re: translations in Dunglison's Dictionary preface 1968 March 15-26 (Box-folder 06:39)
        - Letter from H.L. Hudson (Lea & Febiger) 1968 October 31 (Box-folder 06:40)
        - Correspondence between C.L. Gemmill and Dorothy Hanks (National Library of Medicine), re: dictionaries 1968 November 11-1970 July 8 (Box-folder 06:41)
        - Correspondence between Lester S. King (AMA) and C.L. Gemmill, re: "Robley Dunglison's 'A New Dictionary...'" 1970 May 11-November 12 (Box-folder 06:42)
        - Letter from Joan Darling (Osler Library, McGill University), re: medical dictionaries 1970 June 8 (Box-folder 06:43)
        - Letter from John L. Thornton (St. Barts Hospital Medical College), re: medical dictionaries 1970 June 9 (Box-folder 06:44)
        - Letter from E. Gaskell (Wellcome Trust), re: medical dictionaries 1970 June 17 (Box-folder 06:45)
        - Letter from W.S. Weedon to C.L. Gemmill, re: medical dictionaries [1970 July 1] (Box-folder 06:46)
        - Letter to Harold Bloomquist (Editor, Bulletin of the Medical Library Association) from C.L. Gemmill, with copy of 'Dictionary' 1970 October 20 (Box-folder 06:47)
        - Letter from 'Atch' to C.L. Gemmill, re: dictionary manuscript [ca. 1970] (Box-folder 06:48)
        - Memo from J.B.B. to C.L. Gemmill, re: medical dictionaries, and notes n.d. (Box-folder 07:01)
        - Correspondence between C.L. Gemmill and Saul Jarcho, re: "Robley Dunglison's A New Dictionary of Medical Science" 1972 January 27 (Box-folder 07:02)
      - Other items
        - Photographs of pages from Dunglison's Dictionary n.d. (Box-folder 07:03)
        - Editions of Dunglison's Dictionary and locations n.d. (Box-folder 07:04)
      - Manuscripts
        - Robley Dunglison's A New Dictionary of Medical Science, draft (partial) n.d. (Box-folder 07:05)
        - "Robley Dunglison's 'A New Dictionary of Medical Science'" handwritten draft n.d. (Box-folder 07:06)
        - Marked up copies of "Robley Dunglison's A New Dictionary of Medical Science, 1833" n.d. (Box-folder 07:07)
  - History of Medicine at UVA
    - Correspondence between William B. Bean and C.L. Gemmill, re: Walter Reed, jamboree/symposium 1968 March 28-1969 June 3 (Box-folder 07:08)
    - W.B.Bean to C.L. Gemmill, re: Dunglison, UVA Medical History 1968 March 29-1973 September 17 (Box-folder 07:09)
    - History of Medicine Student Essay Contest [1970] (Box-folder 07:10)
    - Wilhelm Moll to Harry J Warthen, re: History of Medicine at UVA Medical School 1972 October 19 (Box-folder 07:11)
  - Medical Numismatics
    - Letters
      - Letter from Administration of Money and Medals (France) to C.L. Gemmill, re: catalogues (French) 1952 October 14 (Box-folder 07:12)
      - Catalogue of Medals for sale (French) 1950 (Box-folder 07:13)
      - Catalogue of French Medals 1952 January 1 (Box-folder 07:14)
      - Correspondence between American Numismatic Society and C.L. Gemmill 1969 January 25-1972 August 11 (Box-folder 07:15)
      - Letters from P. Rijlant to C.L. Gemmill, re: commemorative medals 1971 March 30-1972 June 2 (Box-folder 07:16)
      - "Aesculapius" Vol. 1, No. 1, published by the Medical Heritage Society 1971 (Box-folder 07:17)
      - Photographs of ancient coins from the British Museum [1972] (Box-folder 07:18)
      - Letter from Ethel A. Franklin to C.L. Gemmill, re: International Physiological Congresses 1972 March 18 (Box-folder 07:19)
      - Letter from A.V. Hill to C.L. Gemmill, re: Physiological Congress medals 1972 March 25 (Box-folder 07:20)
      - Correspondence between Saul Jarcho and C.L. Gemmill, re: Coins of Cyrene 1972 April 4-11 (Box-folder 07:21)
      - Letter from Hans Schaefer to C.L. Gemmill, re: Physiological Congree in Heidelberg 1972 April 6 (Box-folder 07:22)
      - Letters to C.L. Gemmill from C. Marmomoy (University College, London), re: Physiological Congress medals 1972 April 7-1973 July 10 (Box-folder 07:23)
      - Letters from Franklin N. Furness (New York Academy of Medicine) to C.L. Gemmill, re: Commemorative medals 1972 December 12-1973 January 23 (Box-folder 07:24)
      - Letter to C.L. Gemmill from Ralph R. Sonneschein (UCLA), re: Physiological Congress medals 1973 June 19 (Box-folder 07:25)
    - Other items
      - Reprint of "The Coinage of Conrad the First of Jerusalem", Spink & Son's Numismatic Circular 1965 October (Box-folder 07:26)
      - Reprint of "Stonehenge and the Druids" from Spink's Numismatic Circular 1971 February (Box-folder 07:27)
      - Reprint of "Medieval and European Coins" by N. du Quesne-Bird [1971] (Box-folder 07:28)
      - "The Coin-types of Selinus and the Legend of Empedocles" by A.H. Lloyd n.d. (Box-folder 07:29)
      - List of Medals from International Physiological Congresses n.d. (Box-folder 07:30)
      - Figure from "Coins of Cyrene" [1972] (Box-folder 07:31)
      - Figure 1 from "Medical Numismatic Notes XI", medal from IUPS Congress in Brussels, 1904 1973 July 2 (Box-folder 07:32)
      - Figure 2 from "Medical Numismatic Notes XI", medal from IUPS Congress in Heidelburg, 1907 [1973] (Box-folder 07:33)
      - Figure 3 from "Medical Numismatic Notes XI", medal from IUPS Congress in Vienna, 1910 [1973] (Box-folder 07:34)
      - Figure 4 from "Medical Numismatic Notes, XI", medal from IUPS Congress in Groningen, 1913 [1973] (Box-folder 07:35)
      - Figure 5 from "Medical Numismatic Notes, XI", medal from IUPS Congress in Paris, 1920 [1973] (Box-folder 07:36)
      - Figure 6 from "Medical Numismatic Notes, XI", medal from IUPS Congress in Stockholm, 1926 [1973] (Box-folder 07:37)
      - Figure 7 from "Medical Numismatic Notes, XI", medals from 5 IUPS Congresses, 1929-1965 [1973] (Box-folder 07:38)
      - Figure from "Medical Numismatic Notes, XIV", medal from IUPS Congress in Edinburgh, 1923 1973 December 26 (Box-folder 07:39)
      - Slides of International Physiological Congress Commemorative Medal n.d. (Box-folder 07:40)
    - Manuscripts
      - "Coins of Cyrene" handwritten draft n.d. (Box-folder 07:41)
      - "Medical Numismatics: Coins of Cyrene" typed draft n.d. (Box-folder 07:42)
      - "Medical Numismatics: Coins of Cyrene" n.d. (Box-folder 07:43)
      - Handwritten draft "Commemorative Medals Issued at the International Physiological Congresses" n.d. (Box-folder 07:44)
      - Partial Handwritten Draft "Commemorative Medals Issued at the International Physiological Congresses" n.d. (Box-folder 07:45)
      - "Medical Numismatic Notes: Commemorative Medals Issued at the International Physiological Congresses" typed and handwritten n.d. (Box-folder 07:46)
      - "Medical Numismatic Notes: Commemorative Medals Issued at the International Physiological Congresses" n.d. (Box-folder 07:47)
      - Typed and handwritten draft of "Medical Numismatic Notes XII: Commemorative Medals Issued at the International Physiological Congresses" n.d. (Box-folder 07:48)
      - "Medical Numismatic Notes XII: Commemorative Medal Issued at the International Physiological Congress" n.d. (Box-folder 07:49)
  - Orchids/Theophrastus
    - Letters
      - Letters from W.D.A. Smith to C.L. Gemmill, re: "Doctor Syntax" 1969 April 21-30 (Box-folder 08:01)
      - Letter from C.L. Gemmill to the Editors of Loeb Classical Library, re: orchid and Theophrastus 1966 August 15 (Box-folder 08:02)
      - Correspondence between C.L. Gemmill and N. Pelham Wright, re: orchids and diabetes 1966 August 15-21 (Box-folder 08:03)
      - Correspondence between C.L. Gemmill and Phillip H. DeLacy (Cornell), re: Theophrastus (1966 September 16-October 7)-1973 (Box-folder 08:04)
      - Correspondence between C.L. Gemmill and R.E. Dengler, re: Theophrastus translastion (1966 October 7-November 22)-1973 (Box-folder 08:05)
      - Letter from E. Gaskell to C.L. Gemmill, re: Theophrastus, silphium poem 1966 October 24 (Box-folder 08:06)
      - Correspondence between Richard E. Schultes (Harvard) and C.L. Gemmill, re: orchids 1967 February 10-June 30 (Box-folder 08:07)
      - Correspondence between C.L. Gemmill and R.F. Voight (University of Illinois), re: orchids 1967 February 13-20 (Box-folder 08:08)
      - Letters from C.H. Dodson and Julia F. Morton (University of Miami) to C.L. Gemmill, re: orchids 1967 February 13-May 3 (Box-folder 08:09)
      - Letter to C.L. Gemmill from Lothian Lynas (New York Botanical Gardens), re: orchids 1967 February 16 (Box-folder 08:10)
      - Letter to C.L. Gemmill from Laura Rieger (Smith Kline & French Laboratories), re: orchids 1967 February 16 (Box-folder 08:11)
      - Letter to C.L. Gemmill from Charlotte Kenton (National Library of Medicine), re: orchids 1967 February 17 (Box-folder 08:12)
      - Letter to C.L. Gemmill from George Motoasca (S.B. Penick & Co.), re: orchids 1967 February 17 (Box-folder 08:13)
      - Letters to C.L. Gemmill from National Agriculture Library and National Library of Medicine, re: orchids 1967 February 20-28 (Box-folder 08:14)
      - Letter to C.L. Gemmill from Peter A. Hyypio (Cooperative Extension, New York State), re: orchids 1967 February 24 (Box-folder 08:15)
      - Letter to C.L. Gemmill from G.C.K. Dunsterville, re: orchids 1967 February 25 (Box-folder 08:16)
      - Letter from C.L. Gemmill to Robert T. Gunther (Oxford University), re: orchids 1967 March 6 (Box-folder 08:17)
      - Letter from C.L. Gemmill to Albert J. Oakes, Jr. (Consultant, Naval Medical School), re: orchids 1967 July 13 (Box-folder 08:18)
      - Letter to C.L. Gemmill from Jean-Claude Garreta (Dijon Public Library) (French), re: Theophrastus 1967 August 18 (Box-folder 08:19)
      - Letters from E. Gaskell (Librarian, The Wellcome Trust) to C.L. Gemmill, re: references 1969 June 26-1970 April 28 (Box-folder 08:20)
      - Correspondence between C.L. Gemmill and M.A. Monegier du Sorbier (Institute de Recherche de Textes) (French), re: greek texts 1970 February 9-July 6 (Box-folder 08:21)
      - Letter to C.L. Gemmill from C.B. Schmitt (University of Leeds), re: Theophrastus 1970 May 9 (Box-folder 08:22)
    - Other items
      - National Library of Medicine search requests, orchids n.d. (Box-folder 08:23)
      - Orchid Journal Article reprints 1944-1962 (Box-folder 08:24)
      - "Translation of Theophrastus: Historia Pantarum" by Dr. Robert E. Dengler n.d. (Box-folder 08:25)
      - Pages from folder marked "Origin of word orchid" n.d. (Box-folder 08:26)
    - Manuscripts
      - "The Missing Passage in Hort's Translation of Theophrastus", early drafts n.d. (Box-folder 08:27)
      - Edited draft of "Missing Passage" and correspondence between Saul Jarcho and C.L. Gemmill 1972 February 10-15 (Box-folder 08:28)
  - Squill
    - Letters
      - Correspondence between Saul Jarcho (New York Academy of Medicine) and C.L. Gemmill, re: squill 1972 May 10-1973 May 16 (Box-folder 08:29)
      - Letter from Robert V. Cuddihy (Sandoz Pharmaceuticals) to C.L. Gemmill, re: squill references 1972 June 7 (Box-folder 08:30)
      - Letter from E. Gaskell (Wellcome Institute of the History of Medicine) to C.L. Gemmill, re: squill references 1973 January 16 (Box-folder 08:31)
    - Other items
      - Chemical notes on squill and similar molecules n.d. (Box-folder 08:32)
      - Squill figure and legend n.d. (Box-folder 08:33)
      - Bibliographical Search evaluation for 'squill' by C.L. Gemmill 1972 May 17 (Box-folder 08:34)
      - Photocopied article on squill-"Clinical efficacy of squill glucosides" 1973 January 4 (Box-folder 08:35)
      - Photocopy of "Squill Studied Historically" 1910 February 5 (Box-folder 08:36)
      - Photocopy of "Bulbus Scillae" n.d. (Box-folder 08:37)
      - Photocopy of "Pharmacology of Sixty-four Cardiac Glycosides and aglycones" 1954 March 26 (Box-folder 08:38)
    - Manuscript
      - "Pharmacology of Squill" handwritten draft n.d. (Box-folder 08:39)
      - Letter to Saul Jarcho from C.L. Gemmill with typed copies of "The Pharmacology of Squill" 1973 February 1 (Box-folder 08:40)
- Series V: Journal Reprints
  - "Metabolic Activity of Tumor Cells", (speech?) with corrections in C.L. Gemmill's handwriting n.d. (Box-folder 08:41)
  - "Greek Medical Papyri", includes photograph of figure 1 n.d. (Box-folder 08:42)
  - "The Missing Passage in Hort's Translation of Theophrastus", final version n.d. (Box-folder 08:43)
  - Reprint from Biochemistry Magazine (German) "Uber den Tatigkeitsstoffwechsel in Kohlenhydratarmen Kaltblutermusken" 1932 February 1 (Box-folder 08:44)
  - Reprint of "The Influence of 3, 3', 5-Triiodo-L-Thyronine on the survival time of mice with tuberculosis and pneumococcosis" 1958 October 22 (Box-folder 08:45)
  - Reprint of "The Educational Work of Robley Dunglison, MD at the University of Virginia" 1960 June (Box-folder 08:46)
  - Reprint of "Thomas Linacre and John Caius: Medical Humanists of the Renaissance" 1962 January (Box-folder 08:47)
  - "Silphium", inscribed 'To Daphne', reprint 1966 July-August (Box-folder 08:48)
  - Reprint of "The Notebook of Robley Dunglison, Student of Clinical Medicine in Edinburgh, 1815-1816" 1967 (Box-folder 08:49)
  - "The Nonesuch Press: Books from the Private Library of Chalmers L. Gemmill, MD" 1970 April (Box-folder 08:50)
  - "The Greek Concept of Diabetes" reprint 1972 September (Box-folder 08:51)
  - Bulletin of the New York Academy of Medicine, containing "Medical Numismatic Notes XI" 1973 June (Box-folder 08:52)
  - Reprint of "The Pharmacology of Squill" 1974 June (Box-folder 08:53)
  - "Publications Department of Pharmacology, University of Virginia School of Medicine" 1947-53 (Box-folder 08:54)
    Contains 44 reprints by C.L. Gemmill, W.F. Kremer, V. Pertzoff, D.T. Watts, G.H. Richmond, J.G. Hilton, D.R.H. Gourley, G.C. Hall, E.M. Bowman, R.L. Plunkett, C.R. Bauer, J.M. Watkins, H.E. Evert, W.P. Bass, H.F. Chase, and J.T. Matschiner.